Okay. So, I'm going put my name
and a description.
All right. Um, create an array of pizza
the shop sells. Eats pizza should be
pizza should be an object with keys name
price is vegetarian. Okay. So what I'm
going to do is I'm going to say
um let pizza shop
pizzas equal array and in that array
there are objects. So I'm going to say
name
and let's put cheese pizza here.
Um price we're going to put $8.99
and is vegetarian.
We'll set to true.
Um and then we'll put a comma and then
I'm going to copy this down to get
three. So I'm going to put in
veggie supreme
that is $9.99.
And then I'm going to put in barbecue
chicken,
which is $11.99
and is not vegetarian. So I'm going to
make that false. Okay, so it said create
an array. Um, it should have objects
with keys, name, price, and is
vegetarian. Add at least three pizzas.
And then print the array. Okay, so I'm
just going to say console.log
pizza shop pizzas. I'm going to save
this. I'm going to go live.
And
if I inspect in my console, I have an
array of three items. And there are the
three objects. Great. Okay, let's move
to the next problem. Problematically add
problematically programmatically add a
new pizza object to the array. Print the
updated array. Okay. Well, if we want to
programmatically add something to an
array, we access the array and then we
use push. And what do we push in? Well,
we want to push in a new object with the
name of meat lovers.
Um, the price of $12.99
and
the is vegetarian is false.
And then print the array console.log
pizza shop pizzas. So, if we save this
and we go over, we can see that the
first one has one, two, three items in
it. The second one has one, two, three,
four items, and the last one is this
meat lovers pizza. Great. Um, use the
spread operator to make a copy of the
pizza array and add a calzone at the end
of it. Do not change the original. Okay,
so important caveat here. Um, the spread
operator only works on the item that
you're applying it to. So if we apply it
to an array, it'll spread out all of the
things in the array. This array is
storing objects, but the way objects are
stored is it's just storing a reference
to where that object is located. We
would also need to spread out each
object. So the best way to do this is to
use a map function. So I'm going to say
let new pizza shop
um array. I'm going to set it equal to
pizza shop pizzas.m map. So I'm going to
say take each item out of the array. So
this is each object
and what I want you to do is I want you
to
create a new object and in that object I
want to spread out whatever the item is.
So, it's going to come in here, grab
cheese, cheese cheese pizza, and it's
going to take those and spread them out.
And then it will return the array. All
right. Once I'm finished mapping it,
um,
I want to add a cowzone at the end. So
I'll say new pizza shop array
um dot push
um
need to make an object where the name is
calzone.
The price is $7.99
and it is not vegetarian. So is
vegetarian is false. Okay. And then
we'll need to console.log log both
arrays to show that the first array
didn't change. So, we'll do pizza shop
pizzas and console.log
um new pizza shop array.
We'll save this. We'll come over. We've
got our first one, our second one with
meatlovers. Um
and then we get that exact same array
again because we're printing it without
the change. And then we get a different
array because we're printing it with our
cal zone. And so, we've successfully
done that step. So, we use the spread
operator to make a copy of the array.
Okay. Use array.mmap to make a new array
of just the pizza names and print the
result. Okay. So, I'll say let pizza
names equal array. Whoa.
Equal pizza shop pizzas map.
Actually, I'm going to do the full one
that has the calzone in it. So, I'll say
new pizza shop array map. And I want to
take each item out of the array. And I
want to return item.name.
And then we'll console.log
pizza names.
Save that. Come over. Check our work.
Sure enough, cheese pizza, veggies,
supreme, barbecue, chicken, meatlovers,
and calzone. Okay. Use array.filter to
make a new array of only vegetarian
pizzas. So I'll say let veggie pizzas
equal um new pizza shop array.
And I want to take each item out of the
array.
And I want to filter to where item
is vegetarian is true. Or in other
words, I can just say where item is
vegetarian because in this case
vegetarian is true false. So we'll
console.log
veggie pizzas. Save. Come over and we
get cheese pizza is vegetarian and
veggie supreme is vegetarian. If we look
at our list above, um barbecue, chicken,
meat lovers, and calzone are not
vegetarian. So, we successfully filtered
our array. Great. Um now, let's move on
to reducing the array. Um use array.
calculate total cost if you bought one
of each pizza. Okay. So, I'll say let
total cost equal um new pizza shop
array.
reduce takes in a function that previous
and current value and
um what we want to do is we want to take
return the previous value plus the
current value price because current is
going to be an object from the array. If
we look at our array each one has a
price. So if we say current.pric that
will pull out the price and add it on to
the previous. Now, as a caveat here,
because previous would normally start as
the first item of the array, and that's
an object, that is not where we want to
start. We want our current to start
there. So, if we want that, then we need
to add an extra parameter here. And
we're going to start our count at zero.
And that should reduce it. So, let's
console.log
the total cost
and double check our work. And here it
is. 51.95. if you want to buy one of
each pizza. I definitely don't think I
want to buy that many pizzas. Um, we'll
sort the pizzas by price from cheapest
to most expensive. All right, let sorted
array equal new pizza shop array dot
sort
um
cheapest to most expensive is in
ascending order. So if you remember dots
sort takes an array with a and b and you
need to do some subtraction. A minus b
will put it into ascending order.
Remember because the a comes first. A is
in ascending. But the problem is we're
not sorting them by the object. We are
sorting them by the object's uh price
attribute. So we'll say a.pric minus
b.pric
and we'll console.log sorted array.
Whoa. sort sorted array.
Save that. And if we come here, we can
see the cowzone is $7.99, cheese pizza
is $8.99, $9.99, $11.99, and $12.99. So,
we've successfully sorted that array.
Now, we need to dstructure the first
pizza in the previous array into
separate variables for its name and
price. Print them. Okay. So, if we want
to do that, we'll say let
and it's an object. The first item in
the array is an object. So, we'll say
let name and price
equal um sorted array at the zero
position. So, we're saying go into the
array, grab the first item, break out
its name and price, and then console.log
those. So, we're going to console.log
name and price. We'll save that. If we
come over zone and 799 is the name and
price, and we console.log calzone and
799. So, we successfully dstructured
that object. Now we need to create a
function called find pizza by name. So
const find pizza by name equals new
function that should take in a pizza
array and a name and it should return
um the matching pizza object or null if
not found. Okay, so it sounds like what
we want to do is we want to say let
results equal
pizza array filter and um we're
filtering it where we take each item out
of the array and we return it if item
dot name
is exactly equal to the name that they
provided us. If it is we're going to
return that. So filter filters down to
where this condition is met. Um so if
this condition is met where the item
name is equal to this name. So let's say
we put in cheese. Um if it finds cheese
pizza it'll return it. If it doesn't
then it will not add it to the list and
it will just return an empty list. So
this tells us that we need to return
null if it's not found. So what we want
to do is we say if results.length length
is greater than zero, meaning if we
found something, then we're going to
return the results.
Otherwise,
we're going to return null. Okay. Um, so
takes in a pizza array with a name,
returns matching pizza object or null if
found, test it with two names. So, we're
going to console who console.log
and we are going to take um find pizza
by name. Uh, let's give it this sorted
array and let's give it the name cheese
pizza
and then we'll copy this down and we'll
give it orange chicken pizza which is
definitely not in the array. So if we
come over here um we get an array with
just cheese pizza and we get null
meaning that this one worked as well. So
our function correctly works. Now, we
need to create an array where each
element is another array representing uh
the pizza name and the price. And we
need to print that array. So, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to take our
sorted array and I'm going to map it.
I'm going to take each item out of that
sorted array and I'm going to return
an array that has item.name
and item price in an array. And we're
going to store this new
letfal array equal our sorted array
where we've mapped those. And I'm going
to console.log
our final array. Save this. Come over.
And here we can see we've got calzone
$799, cheese pizza $8.99, veggie supreme
$9.99, barbecue chicken and meat lovers.
And it's um it is an array of arrays
with the pizza name and the price. And
that concludes this walkthrough.